Guide to the Zach Stewart Papers M2206
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Zach Stewart papers
1964-1974
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stewart, Zach
M2206
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Zach Stewart and the architecture firm Osborne & Stewart worked with Stewart Brand and many others to create arts events in the 1960s, including America Needs Indians, Sensoriums, and the Trips Festival. They were also involved with an unrealized design project for the United Farmworkers in Delano, California.
Related Materials
Stanford Special Collections also holds the Stewart Brand papers (M1237: https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4688803).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Audiovisual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Zach Stewart; 2017. Accession MSS 2017-059.
Scope and Contents
Zachary "Zach" R. Stewart is an architect whose firm with fellow Stanford alumnus Dan Osborne worked with Stewart Brand and others on a number of mid-to-late 1960s arts/multi-media/happenings in the San Francisco Bay Area and around the country, including the inter-related America Needs Indians and Sensorium series, as well as staging the Trips Festival at Longshoreman's Hall in 1966. Much of the coordination and logistics, as well as the design and publicity, were performed by Osborne & Stewart. America Needs Indians as an organization (it was also the name of several events) was located at the firm's offices at 25 Hotaling Place. Osborne & Stewart was also part of an unrealized project to design the United Farmworkers Organizing Committee headquarters in Delano, California.
Happenings (Art); Architects.; Installations (Art) -- United States.; Indians of North America -- Public opinion; Stewart, Zach; Stewart, Zach; Brand, Stewart; United Farm Workers
- Series 1. America Needs Indians
  Scope and Contents
  Perhaps named for Iktomi's 1937 book, America Needs Indians was both a movement and a series of art happening/performance/installations involving music, dance, images, and other sensory elements, ostensibly about American Indians.
  - Brand/Stewart correspondence re: ANI, Sensoriums, etc. (copies) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - correspondence, January-May 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - correspondence, June-September 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - correspondence, October-December 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - correspondence, 1966 etc. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A few letters date from 1967, 1969 and 1974.
  - slides, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - transparencies (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - publicity (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - originals- exhibit design, draft text, Brand photograph (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - notes, memoranda, sketches, other logistics (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Also includes some Sesnorium material.
- Series 2. Sensoriums
  As defined by Stewart in 1966 article, "A Sensorium is 'son et lumiere' -- sound and light." This series of multimedia events took place at such places as The Committee and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art. Most were numbered, although some presentations repeated a theme. Several Sensoriums were also titled "America Needs Indians." Later productions, such as those at Grace Cathedral, sometimes did not refer to themselves as Sensoriums.
  - Sensorium 1-6 calendar flier with drafts (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sensorium 6: America Needs Indians, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sensorium 7: America Needs Indians, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sensorium 9 & 22: The Architecture of Energy, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Yin & Yang: I.D.S.A. Sensorium (San Francisco Art Institute), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Four Thousand Years Sensorium (Grace Cathedral), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - A Vigil for the Great Family (Grace Cathedral), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series 3. Trips Festival, 1966
  The Trips Festival was also billed as America Needs Indians/Sensorium 9 By Stewart Brand and Zach Stewart. Osborne and Stewart were credited in the program with "Environment." Material includes correspondence, notes, sketches, and bills and receipts for items that were rented or purchased in order to stage the event. Although there is some correspondence with promoter Bill Graham, there are no references the bands that played or any contractual paperwork. However, the file does include the two-sided black & white handbill designed by Wes Wilson, and a few slides taken at the event.
  - slides, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - handbills, correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - notes, sketches, bills, receipts, etc., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series 4. Hoving Celebration- Parks, 1967
  Billed as "A Celebration of Tom Hoving" or "A Celebration of the Future," this event seems to have been organized by Osborne & Stewart, but the incomplete file provides relatively little information.
  - notes, press releases, correspondence, etc. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series 5. Ernest Lowe "Don't Cry For Me Babey", 1966
  Osborne & Stewart provided logistical support for photographer Ernest Lowe's installation about farmworkers titled "Don't Cry For Me Babey: Farm Labor Environment." The exhibition was presented at San Francisco's de Young Museum September 10th-October 11, 1966. More information about Lowe can be found at his website: http://ernestlowe.com.
  - notes, text drafts, correspondence, fliers, reviews, etc. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 6. National Farmworkers Service Center, Delano project, 1967
  Osborne & Stewart was was involved with the development of the United Farmworkers Organizing Committee headquarters in Delano, California. titled officially the National Farmworkers Service Center. It was to be on the same property as 40 Acres. The project was never completed but it illustrates the aspirations of the organization in the Fall of 1967. Included is correspondence with UFW Executive Director LeRoy Chatfield and builder Jim Holland. Cesar Chavez is mentioned frequently but there are no letters from or to him. Other material includes notes, sketches and memoranda. There are also many photographs whicyh are probably related to the Delano project. No photographer is credited, but some correspondence does refer to photographs. Included are images of Cesar Chavez, Delores Huerta, and UFW activity, as well as argicultural work, construction, and residences. Osborne & Stewart also worked with photographer Ernest Lowe in an installation about farm work, so some of the photos may be his. There is also a slideshow that was assembled to demonstrate the project to the UFWOC membership at a Thanksgiving gathering in 1967. The slides have been removed from the original carousel. An audio reel probably accompanies the slideshow.
  - notes, correspondence, sketches ,etc. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - photographs: farmworkers, Central Valley, UFW, etc. (Box 3)
    Distinct series of prints with numbers and punch holes for binding. No photographer or identifying notes present (may also be related to Lowe exhibit).
  - photographs: farmworkers, Central Valley, UFW, etc. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    No photographer or identifying notes present (may also be related to Lowe exhibit).
  - photographs, snapshots, etc.: farmworkers, Central Valley, UFW, etc. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Some images suggest they were taken as part of the planning for the Service Center. Some correspondence refers to these being taken, but no photographer or identifying notes present on the prints. Some may also be related to the Ernest Lowe exhibit.
  - UFW/Delano slides from carousel presentation (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Delano Show 5" audio reel (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series 7: oversize material
  - Mills College Club of San Francisco "The Look of the City" handbill featuring Zach Stewart & John Vietor; 2 Stewart Brand photographs; flier and two posters for Whale, Pelican & Pygmy Forest Sensorium at Grace Cathedral March 19, 1971; Pacific Sun review of SFMOMA Sensorium May 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)